Norman J. Feitelson Papers VHP2006/27
CCSU Veterans History Project
Norman J. Feitelson Papers
Bulk, 1943-1946
1943 - 1946, 2006
VHP2006/27
CCSU Veterans History Project
289.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of Norman J. Feitelson as he served in The U.S. Army Infantry during World War II in Europe. The collection contains personal military record, medals, newspaper clippings, and publications about his infantry unit.
Feitelson, Norman J., 1924 -
Biographical/Historical note
Norman Feitelson tried to enlist in the U.S. Air Force in 1942, but failed the entrance exam due to an eye test. He then decided to wait to enter the service until he was drafted. He was drafted into the U.S. Army with 18 others from Waterbury, Ct in June of 1943. He went to basic training at Camp Edwards, which was in Cape Cod, Ma. He attended basic training for eleven months, where he learned how to be a range setter for an anti-aircraft unit. Although his unit (836th Anti-aircraft Battalion), was supposed to ship overseas in anticipation of D-Day, instead the unit was disassembled and the soldiers were broken into different divisions. Feitelson was placed in an infantry unit, and shipped to Fort Dix for infantry and artillery training. He was then sent to Louisiana and Fort Bragg before going overseas. Feitelson sailed to Scotland with 30,000 other soldiers and was assigned to the 5th infantry division, 11th infantry regiment as a replacement just after the Battle of the Bulge. His job in this unit was to operate an automatic rifle which weighed 17 ½ pounds, and had to be carried everywhere. Just two days after landing in France to join his unit, he experienced combat during the Battle of Bitburg. On his very first patrol he saw men killed. In March of 1945, his unit was part of the crossing of the Rhine, where they heard the famous speech given by General Patton before the battle that ensued. When the surrender of Germany was officially announced, his unit moved into Austria and Czechoslovakia, where it was their duty to "clean up" units that were not aware that they had surrendered. They also liberated one of the satellite concentration camps in Czechoslovakia, where Feitelson's knowledge of Yiddish came in handy for interpretation purposes. In June of 1945, the soldiers were sent back to the United States, and given a 30 day leave to go home. While Feitelson was back in Connecticut the end of the war was announced, so instead of reporting for infantry duty, he was sent to Fort Campbell where he began playing and refereeing basketball for the army team. He was discharged from the U.S. Army in February of 1946, and used the GI Bill to obtain his degree in elementary education from the Teacher's College of Connecticut in New Britain, Ct.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
United States. Army. Infantry Division, 104th. Field Artillery Battalion, 385th.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 11th..; Australia; Camp Edwards (Mass.); Czechoslovakia; Fort Bragg (N.C.); Fort Campbell (Ky. and Tenn.); Fort Dix (N.J.); France; Germany; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Europe; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Czechoslovakia; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/27.I
  - Discharge papers, Feb. 3, 1946; VHP2006/27.I.1; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Norman Feitelson's Medals, circa 1940s; VHP2006/27.I.2; 6.0 Digital objects
  - Letter from National Archives and Records Administration about his Army military records, Dec. 5, 2005; VHP2006/27.I.3; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Interview synopsis, Dec. 22, 2006; VHP2006/27.I.4
- Series II: Publications, VHP2006/27.II
  - The Fifth Infantry Division in the ETO (book), 1945; VHP2006/27.II.1; 258.0 Digital objects; Headquaters Fifth Infantry Division. The Fifth Division Historical Section.
  - Connecticut Men of the 5th - Red Devils - Division pamphlet, August 1945; VHP2006/27.II.2; 12.0 Digital objects
  - Articles in the Republican-American newspaper about Norman Feitelson, 2000s; VHP2006/27.II.3; 3.0 Digital objects
    Scope and Contents note
    "Long overdue medals arrive: Feitelson honored for WWII deed" by Tom Kabelka and "Feitelson's lifetime of stories" by Joe Palladino.
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2006/27.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/27.III
    - Norman J. Feitelson military photo, Oct. 1, 1944; VHP2006/27.III.1
    - Norman J. Feitelson at the time of interview, Dec. 22, 2006; VHP2006/27.III.2
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/27.IIIb
    - Oral history interview with Norman J. Feitelson, Dec. 22, 2006; VHP2006/27.III.2; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2006/27, Box VHP Interview 2006)